okay and welcome to the
December
2020 Eno seminar which will be presented
by y bber from MC University although
currently
inar will Beed
so um welcome
yell and um we will have we we're muted
there for a
moment thank you um yell did um you did
your your PhD in Amsterdam with Eric
gelt is that right
and um completed
postto yeah sorry sorry I was just I I
still had the YouTube link open so I was
hearing double sounds so it's what's
going wrong but now now now we're now
I'm full Focus yeah
good the joys of of the zoom uh seminar
exactly so you are currently you have
moved to a postto position in mcari
University as of sometime during this um
decade of a year and will continue uh in
that position for at least another year
as well if at any point you actually get
south of the Equator yeah yeah so it's a
it's a three-year position but indeed so
far um I've been working remotely but
yeah as everybody actually so
yeah indeed so um the we we have a few
people logged on and we are expecting a
couple of live participants for the
discussion later which ought to be um
Lively and interesting I did now um
I mentioned when we spoke before the
possibility we we might uh give a signal
boost to something if you have come
across a reading or uh some kind of
resource in recently that you'd like to
you think well that's that's something
the Eno Community might be interested in
in knowing about have you come across
any good papers or yeah wait I'll I'll
I'll um share the screen I made a little
commercial break slide you can see it
now right yeah yeah so uh uh
here it is uh so uh on the left uh
there's son Dean's uh book an active
Psychiatry we just had a a reading group
on it with the with the people in
Amsterdam uh and I can warmly recommend
it I think it Deals Deals with the
topics of Psychiatry but also pushes an
activism further in a number of
directions mainly that of the notion of
values uh I think in the more
existentialist Direction and has some uh
uh really good points in in developing a
more relational realist metaphysics for
an activism so I really uh enjoy that um
and the other one is a little bit of
Shameless self-promotion uh but I know
many people in an activism are
interested in the links with the with
with the free energy principle I worked
on this in my PhD uh as well and I
received lots of students who who who
really want to work on all that that
that stuff
and uh I just been uh publishing this
preprint uh uh a few days ago where we
share some doubts about the possibility
of such a kind of approach specifically
with the notion of Mark blankets so this
is not what we're going to talk about
today at all but I thought for those
interested in the more free energy
principle kind of things I think this is
a conversation which at some point we
need to have uh with those
people uh
yeah
excellent thank you very much for that
and um I love the idea of a commercial
break we might continue to use that one
as things go on
nice but now I think we have where we
have a good few people online God bless
um the pandemic it has uh pushed people
for fullon internet engagement and uh we
have one or two people coming into the
live session we'll keep them we'll keep
them quiet until later on but in the
meantime uh y if I can invite you toh to
present the December 2020 endel seminar
uh thanks a lot Merck and um so hello
everyone thanks for having me and um I'm
just going to pretend we somehow have
cornered off a little uh a little corner
of the internet and have a chat
among friends uh it's somehow a bit
weird to know that you're being
broadcasted to to to the worldwide web
uh so I treat this as a kind of internal
uh seminar and uh so the topic today is
that topic of my research project in in
mcari uh called the world of the
fingertips embod cognition and the
attention crisis and this is a bit of a
new topic for me and I'm still
experimenting a little bit uh with how
to best introduce introduce it and so
how I've been doing it was kind of
starting with big alarming claims about
the attention economy and the idea that
human attention is being harvested for
commercial gain so this is the kind of
kind of alarming story that you find in
sh zub's uh work the age of surveillance
capitalism and also this is I just have
the books here this very good book by
James Williams stand out of our light um
I can later on share the links to those
books or so uh and in that literature
you find a more or less explicit or
implicit uh view of human nature and
sometimes it's rather
cognitivism is an extremely
behavioristic View
uh there's a lot of evolutionary
psychology in that literature how we're
just wired to be U addicted to the
internet or to smartphones
Etc um and then having presented all
those positions you can show like look
actually there is some some space here
for a more kind of embodied and inactive
position that shows that both the the
kind of vulnerabilities that we have in
relationship to those Technologies but
also the possibility to have somehow in
interacting with them maintain uh some
kind of autonomy um I tried this a few
times and that results in a kind of big
big stroke kind of kind of picture where
you really uh have competing pictures of
human nature um and so today I want to
try something a little bit different and
more trace a little bit my own thinking
and how I arrived at this project and
this really starts from more anactive
principles and arrives in the end about
the logical questions about human nature
and how that how how that works so this
is the experiment for
today and then the starting point now is
is um actually uh something that that I
was reminded of again in in Sonic's book
um and that often in an activism people
write about uh sense making as a kind of
projection of value on a neutral world
so we kind of enct this world we create
it Rec constitute it um and in some
sense that's right right that that that
world is is a co-production of uh uh uh
us uh but there's also something and in
H's terms it might be something like the
tronus of sense making right so in in
activist terms we we find ourselves
making sense of the world and in kind of
the Amsterdam terminology uh we find
ourselves being solicited in a
meaningful Way by a field of affordances
right so we don't choose we don't decide
which things we we are affected by how
we make sense of the world uh but we
find ourselves being affected in this
way and that is actually where agency
starts
um so we encountered this this this
world that is that is not completely of
our own making and of course there's a
lots of aspects there that do contribute
to this to this world of course personal
history typically something like like
history of interactions with the
environment uh the kind of skills that
you have acquired during your lifetime
uh the social material environment
itself uh including all the practices of
the education of attention Etc uh a form
of life the behavior settings I believe
the last answer seminar was was on on on
Behavior setting um the layout of of the
affordance in the
environment and and like making this
list I got to the question like what
what about Technologies what about the
kind of digital Technologies uh uh that
we carry around uh with us and um of
course these aspects here are not
mutually exclusive and I think there's a
lot of overlap between them but these
are more like I think from different
theoretical Vantage points in in
activism you you arrive at some of those
some some of those Concepts a bit more
permanently than other ones um and so I
kind of noticed that I've been showing
uh uh these kind of pictures uh for
years as kind of scenario of the
Hallmark of skilled action
where an agent is engaging with multiple
affordances at the same time and somehow
maintaining a grip on this interaction
with the environment and to my own
embarrassment actually I I suddenly
realized that the amount of technology
that that that's going on in this in
this picture the amount of technological
mediation that that that's going on
here and if you come at it from a more
affordance perspective this really leads
to a couple of embarrassing questions
that I was at least at that point not
able and still not actually able to to
answer properly right so it is this an
affordance um and you might think in
terms of solicitation of invitation
that's definitely the case if you think
about when you read a book
um uh and and the phone is lying next to
you you can definitely can feel the
solicitation the invitation of of
something even without the kind of
push-up messages that you might every
once in a while
encounter um and yes it is an A forance
in the sense you can do lots of things
with it um but other you also might
thinking no no it's the phone itself is
not the affordance it's a kind of
Gateway it's a kind of mediated to
affordances and what what what are the
affordances yeah maybe the apps on it or
the things you can do on the app so
there's a kind of kind of uh uh uh the
phone is a kind of entrance point in a
new kind of uh uh Niche and I didn't
quite have the terminology to to to uh
and the concepts to think about it
um and of course there is a large
history of of what and this is a term I
think that's from uh uh
postphenomenology so kind of more Phil
philosophy of Technology angle to uh uh
uh to phenomenology
and they call this technological
mediation so the mediation of
intentionality through by Technologies
and of course we find this in higher
already about the the hammer well if you
carry the hang the the hammer then the
whole world shows up as for hamable as
so as kind of affording hammering and
the mopon you find the example of the
blind person's can and these are all
forms of the mediation of of of of
intentionality but kind of opening up to
the same world in a different kind of
way at least that's would be my way of
my intuitive way of characterizing this
and then the question is like so what
what about these these uh digital
Technologies right they they don't in a
sense they seem similar that they are
transparent right you see through the
hammer you see it through the cane and
you see it through your phone into
something else uh but rather than
showing up allowing you the world to
show up in a different way it it it
opens it shows up a new kind of world in
which action possibilities are aligned
in a different kind of way so that the
question is like how to think is is
there think about this is there
something like a digital Niche a cyber
Niche is that the right kind of kind of
terminology
um and so I want to as a kind of take a
take a few steps back about how to think
about the influence of technology I want
to to to uh mention this example from
the from the 50s really or the early
60s um and that's that's the example of
the remote control uh for television so
in another book very good book the the
the attention Merchants the subtitle is
the Epic struggle to get inside our
heads um uh the writer Tim Ru uh vividly
captures the kind of sentiment at the at
the end of the 50s about the arrival of
commercial breaks on
television and uh the zened radio
company orders Engineers to kind of find
an antidote against his arrival of of of
Comm commercial brakes and they uh
develop this device that allowed you to
to shoot out commercial uh uh or
advertisements and the the result is
something like an ad blocker of onra
where you can kind of shoot at your
television and mute uh the sound and
later on switch channels Etc and of
course this this is something that we
now know as a as as a remote
control and
uh this was really meant as a kind of
way for consumers to
uh gain and maintain autonomy be able to
decide what you want to to look at uh W
call is the resistance against the
industrialized Harvest of attention I
think this is the kind of terminology
that we find now again in in the
literature on the attention
economy um and then W kind of vividly uh
uh described and this is an abbreviated
quote uh how that that dream of autonomy
was really shortlived so you're right so
the remote control made it almost
effortless practically non-volitional to
redirect our attention in fact in the in
the course of sustained Channel serving
the voluntary aspect of attentional
control may disappear entirely having
thus surrender the mind is simply
jumping about and following whatever
grabs it uh so you can really think here
about the idea like you're sitting late
at night you should be going to bed you
want to go to bed in some sense of
wanting but there is this kind of
Behavioral cycle going on of sustained
uh channel surfing and I think W
highlights a few key points here right
the that something like fision or
executive control seems to be
disappearing uh uh entirely from that
episode um and in a sense in some sense
this the kind of uh disappearance of
control is also the Hallmark of uh the
kind of descriptions of skilled action
that drivers gives kind of kind of
skilled coping skilled mindless coping
uh although this is a Mindless coping
but not in the in the right sense uh of
the world so there there parallel there
between the kind of skilled coping
examples but also of course big
differences so I think Wu present us
here with a puzzle uh and the pieces are
something like friction or sensory motor
effort it becomes so easy uh uh to
change channels uh that we somehow
become more impulsive F and executive
control are are disappearing and the
question is how to put that puzzle
uh together
and so I think what you find here is
really uh and and I'll call it clashing
anthropologies and it's it's
anthropology in a sense it's it's
sketches or pictures of human nature uh
but then that human nature is not
something that's that's immutable and
unchangeable but something that is that
is yeah you might say enacted um so this
remote control is really designed for a
particular kind of agent and that's an
agent who knows what it wants and just
needs the easiest means to realize in
the world what it wants so the kind of
distinction between what what are your
goals what are your
values uh and what you can do if you if
you have a strong distinction between
those then then it's an good advice to
to have um it's it's a less Ideal tool I
think for a situated agent that figures
out in interacting with the world what
it what it wants so the kind of the
goals and the concerns and the
solicitations are not independent of
your interaction with the world but they
shaping each
other um so the kind
of the anthropology of autonomy we are
rational beings we we know what to do
and we just need to uh uh uh shape the
world so that it becomes as easy as
possible for us to know what to to to
realize what we do um I think that in
this case had very unintended
consequences in many cases of uh uh
behavioral design in in in a modern
technology that's not unintended that's
that's completely uh uh intended the
kind of Behavioral effects it is it is
having um so what you find in the
literature really are two two narratives
here on attention but the narratives are
way more than narratives on attention
there narratives on autonomy the
narratives on agency there there there
are the these kind of uh uh um kind of
anthropologies I say um and so I already
mentioned James Williams uh book and
this is stand out of a light you see the
subtitle freedom and resistance in the
attention economy and so this is really
an attempt to
describe uh what our possibilities are
in the in in the age of the attention
economy uh um how how we can think about
Freedom what is at stake uh and how we
can regain
it and part of Williams narrative is uh
is following Herbert Simon in saying
that well there there is historically
there has been a kind of scarcity of of
information and therefore an abundance
of attention but now in this kind of
information Rich times we live in times
of information overload and therefore
scarcity of attention so what we need to
do is put something like a boundary in
place to kind of separate us from from
the information in the environment so
that we can reflect and decide and be
autonomous again um on the other hand we
have a completely different uh narrative
and I think that
narrative uh
um um follows the more more behaviorist
principles so so Nal
writes also I think the subtitles and
the titles are really telling here so
hooked how to build habit forming
products uh and it's a it's a story
about how to get users hooked to your to
your products and that's a story about
you you can make the environment as
inviting as possible but the the the the
the real thing is to get inside the
agent and hack their the habits right so
it's in in environmental competition
there's still a lot of competition
between different kind of companies but
if you can be prior to that and instill
in the user an urge or something like
this to uh uh uh to engage with a
product then then you're really talking
then you're really getting people people
hooped and interestingly in terms of a
kind of quasy phenomenology I think AAL
is really uh closer to the point in
terms of kind of idea of that indeed if
you structure how agents find themselves
in the world what kind of habits they
have how they are solicited by this
world uh then you need to know you don't
need to place interesting things in that
world in in in the world they will look
for it themselves uh so you you really
have hijacked agents in some particular
kind of kind of way and of
course for a this this in a is this is
situated in a general picture of human
nature where in the and we are
behaviorist machines so autonomy and
agency are not really in the cards
anyway so so there's not nothing really
really ethically wrong with the kind of
kind of hooked model James Williams has
something more to defend he wants to
have a more robust IDE of autonomy and
freedom that is that is that is at
stake
um so the hope is here that in activism
really can can provide a more realist
realistic anthropology uh and I think
this the success of the attention
Merchant shows that we are situated
beings uh formed through our interaction
with the
environment uh and autonomy is not
something that puts a boundary in place
between us and the world but it needs to
be achieved through interactions with
the environment so that that that that's
where it kind of kind of combine the
points from from a and Williams I think
um and if
um I think we're doing still right qu
time right right
then good yeah I think I think we're
yeah we good of time then then I'll make
a little Excursion
through Neuroscience hopefully to get
back to the to the to the same point so
I've been a long-term fan of something
that's called the affordance competition
hypothesis some of you uh uh might note
and I think it's it's a general
framework for for Neuroscience it's very
much in key with with with important an
activist principes principles um
and what you get from there um it's it
of course it's a bit neurocentric but
but but you get there is the idea that
this is a quote from Paul cisc so
decision making is not a single unified
Phenomenon with a single neural
substrate so we should stop thinking
about decision- making as one one thing
but rather a disputed process that
emerges differently across the nervous
system depending on the information that
finally DET determines the
choice um and you see a lot of work at
the moment
um there's a both by C but other people
as well there's there's a recent paper
by Bernard homel which C is a co-author
and says nobody knows what attention is
so it seems that from a neuroscientific
perspective some of those important kind
of constructs that we use in every day
decision- making
attention uh um are not unified single
phenomenon but are things executive
control is another one of them but are
really things that emerge in a
particular kind of uh situation
depending on the layout of the action
possibilities and um so one um important
distinctions that CC makes that is that
between action specification and action
selection um so you see here the this is
a kind of General framework that that
he's having and you see that there if it
if we talk about action selection
there's a lot of projecting to the to
the Bas of gang and if we talk about
action specification there is there is
uh uh more more more more cortical ER
arrows that are that are being drawn um
and in his recent work CC talks about
this as within behavior and between
Behavior selection so you might think
like oh of all the things that I can do
there's there's a selection between
different kind of behaviors and then in
the the classical example of lifting the
cup is uh is that that that's a question
of action specification right so you and
those process happen in parallel that's
not a kind of sequential model but once
you decide uh to to to lift a cup the
specification is something that that's
uh um that's left that that's a
different kind of process and typically
we have more executive control over the
kind of selection process and less over
the specification there's no not much
use in controlling actively where to
where to uh uh uh uh how to grasp the
cup I just want to grasp the the cup um
and
um so the examples he's giving is is um
are related to um the difference between
pointing and grasping for example the
these are these are makak
studies uh
so choosing between pointing and
grasping is a is a is action
selection uh specifying where to point
is action
specification um and so neural this to
be very different mechanisms for these
these these different kind of uh uh
forms of selection I mean you might you
not you might not even call the second
one decision making and so at least from
in intuitively from this perspective
right the fact that we engage with
nowadays with with much of our
environment in a kind of pointing kind
of way makes it that we
make very relevant uh uh behavioral
decisions uh am I going to go on
Facebook I'm going to write the paper
with a swipe of a finger or or or or the
point so we use the kind of from that
kind of perspective we use the kind of
action specification mechanisms for
actually things that that intuitively we
would like to be forms of action
selection and and uh things to be
deliberate um so I think there's a also
big possibility to to combine this more
more neuroscientific angle with the kind
of issues on the attention economy and I
think the kind of work on affordance
competition is very very much in key
with with uh uh with with an activism
and The crucial bit here is that
that from this perspective affordances
right we don't have just like a whole
row of affordances or so right but this
kind of hierarchical organization within
them uh some of them are specification
some of them are are selection and
nested within each other uh and they
each of them have different forms of
cognitive control associated with them
and uh right so let me see uh
um so here we have a different kind of
mismatch I guess between the
Technologies and environment uh and and
and and and the anthropology that we
that we are that we
have um this this a mismatch between the
structure of Digit digital environments
and the structured Behavior or what you
might call the affordance uh uh
competition and of course this is not
something this kind of affordance
competition hierarchy is not something
that's fixed it might be very much kind
dependent on development uh as well but
I think it also gives a set of tools to
rethink uh about our our relationship
with digital uh uh Technologies and in
in much of the more uh uh also the more
postphenomenological literature on on
philosophy of of of of technology and
attention um there's really not much
interesting interesting uh interest in
in cognitive science uh and I think an
activism really has a is in a good
position here to also take these
insights from cognitive science to the
table and still have a robust story
about what we want to achieve
autonomy an agency so to wrap up so I
think an activism is really in a strong
position to to to formulate this
realistic anthropology for the attention
economy and uh this is another talk that
says it has been done I have a paper on
this but this is really this is where my
thinking how how I came from from from
thinking about a fores in this more
towards this more attention economy
topics uh and I think both
neuroscientifically in terms of the
central concept of an activism there's a
really in a good position to to pursue
this kind of project so this is where I
am at the moment and I would look
forward to discuss it with you thank
you that's great thank you um thank you
very much y there you go um so we um we
have at least one of the voice here in
the live session with us and I think we
may yet be joined by one or two um other
latecomers but I guess we'll see if they
show um so I obviously as ever have uh
many comments and questions but I will
also offer the first response to the
non-mar member of the the
discussion
um um I don't there is anything you want
to say yeah uh thanks very much J um
it's it's interesting to see
how considerations from the strong
physicalist realist stance of ecological
psychology the still emerging and not
yet defined feel of an
activism and um soot tech technical
considerations are coming
together I believe that there's an awful
lot of
um unsteadiness in the conceptual
formulations that we're using here which
is one of the reasons that we have these
seminars of course but I want to draw I
want to come to your use of the term
anthropology I
object um anthropology of course as a
discipline has a shameful history of the
vois habits of you privileged European
males going to people who are culturally
distant and um interpreting them from
within their own Christian eurocentric
cultural point of view now anthropology
as a discipline has been through an
awful awful lot and it tries to resist
strongly positivist formulations to to
the extent that it is that it aspires to
to generalize to something called the
anthropos which is a something in
construction but not necessarily
finished um the use of the term
anthropology must be done then in a in a
in a cautious manner when it engages
with scientific discourse now you
introduced a
stoning cultural construct a European
cultural construct the psychological
subject driven by attention with
executive control and
decision-making and you can put
perception in there as well and there
you've got something that we have built
here in the West on a largely platonist
and Christian
Foundation um have constructed
methodologically so when it comes to
attention for example nobody ever really
anymore asks what is attention or does
attention exist they ask how do we
operationalize attention and you have to
ask the same thing about executive
control and decision- making not do they
exist but how do we operationalize them
because if you get too positivist and
realist about those things they go away
so I'm worried about your realistic
anthropology I think what you're doing
by engaging with the psychological
subject in this way I don't think you
can use anthropology I want to I want to
sort of say that's the that's not
appropriate I'm coming from a position
of EXT extrem skepticism with respect to
Scientific psychology so so please
excuse that I don't expect everyone to
share that but I do think the the nature
of
scientific Uh current scientific
practices and the aspirations of a field
called anthropology they there's a great
tension there and so so that's what I
want to draw your attention to good yeah
um so I should confess so I'm I'm
I'm I I wasn't completely aware of of of
these tensions when when when when I was
using this this uh uh the concept of
anthropology
um I think and here I'm also a bit I
mean all of those concepts are are are
troubled right I mean so what what what
is implicit in this
literature you might think is a picture
of human nature but human nature is is
just as troubled as as as as
anthropology
I think for me at least I mean I went
for anthropology as a kind of lighter
notion than than than than human nature
but it's
it's it's a picture of how people make
sense of the world how they arrive at
decisions how they attend what kind of
control they have over their environment
uh and and that picture you can you can
distill from from from uh skinners
Beyond freedom of and dignity and then
you have a picture in which we're
enslave saved by by by by by our
environments and and uh the picture you
can get from it it's implicit in in in
in all the works on the attention
economy there is they
they even if they're pointing outside if
even if they're pointing to to to to all
the all the even like zubov writes about
surveillance capitalism it's not about
human psychology but it it it's it's
about the capitalistic system but it all
operates with a particular kind of
either the liberating agent or or
behavioristic agent or something like
that so I I I want to zoom in on on on
those kind of implicit commitments that
are that that that are make made and I
think
there an activism similarly has has as
as a position of what it is to be a
sense making agent
um that comes along with its own kind of
vulnerabilities and and and getting
those vulnerabilities into view requires
you to somehow make make make
commitments about it
is yeah but but when you say the person
I think you're thinking of people like
you I don't think you're thinking of
this person this is person from tier Del
fuo one of the crowd who was genocided
at the start of the um 20th century um
he met anthropologists they didn't
understand him people of that tribe even
met Charles Darwin Charles Darwin
regarded them as animals which is funny
because Charles Darwin went on to tell
us all that we're animals which is which
is a odd but you can see from his
reaction he didn't understand them and
they had no common basis would you say
that any account of decision making
executive control and attention would
apply to this person as well as to
someone who was brought up within a
capitalist um Western heavily
industrialized society and if not then
it's not anthropology really it's
building something within the I'm going
to say it neoliberal c um secular
capitalist order
um so
um I I mean the story I present about
the role of Technology on on uh um on
everyday life is yes
it's it's the role of Technology on
everyday Western life right I mean that
that that's that that's clear and um for
people like you and me yeah yeah yeah
yeah uh uh and and and and um that's a
story I can tell because that's a story
I have
uh most experienc uh with I I haven't
done research in in in in those kind of
areas so I'm I me very unfair here I'm
I'm sorry so so my the anthropology I
describe has much larger aspirations and
won't be squashed into any particular
Western Viewpoint obviously yeah um but
there's a similar tension isn't there
between the strongly realist commitments
of affordance layouts as described in a
gibsonian framework and um the less
secure commitments to person body agents
individual that Ares within an activism
so there maybe
as as I said the field is is not yet
established so but I yeah isn't it the
persistent tension between ecological
and anactive approaches which some
people don't see as a tension I
absolutely do um but it extends all the
way out then but I think as well sorry
yellow there I mean I as I see it there
is a I mean when when y introduced the
term he introduced it in the plural
right there are multiple anthropologies
no that's right yeah and and as such
there is sort of an inherent recognition
of the boundedness of any of these and
the limitations of any of these rather
than than sort of placing one as as sort
of Superior or more encompassing than
the other but rather the anthropology is
inherent in it's the the implicit
foundation in which um any given
description of a specific behavior or or
cognitive system or cognitive function
is is um
presented maybe just to briefly follow
up I think
the these are
anthropologies in in position in
literature right so their implicit
impositions in the literature rather
than their in persons right so so um so
when I meant realistic I didn't mean so
this is it's it's realistic in the sense
that that it's more
uh closer to to real life but but not
realistic in the sense like this is this
is what happens in person this is in no
it's it's in that sense it's it's it's a
more kind of looking at these positions
in the literature and deriving from them
the kind of implicit commitments they
make to a particular kind of picture of
of of of of human nature uh and that's
inde that that that's a pluralistic
concept without any commitments from my
side at least about how that applies to
uh uh even those in the west and let let
alone to to
any and to kind of any human or so so
something that kind of generalistic
claims I don't I don't think I want to
go there or need to go there
that's great so I I see Eric has joined
I know Eric has a question as well so
I'll I'll pass on to you there hey hey
can you hear me yeah yes yeah hi y
thanks was very interesting I knew
already part of the story of course and
it's good to hear you telling it here um
I have a question you started out
talking about uh technological mediation
and
postphenomenology uh but then you end up
with your positive story which is the
field of a for
es uh in which the field of affordances
plays an important role so I was
wondering what in the end does this talk
about
postphenomenology and technological
mediation do for you as work doesn't do
any work or is it just an idle wheel in
in the in the paper that you that you
just gave uh and um uh and if not then
how will you avoid creating a dichotomy
between technological affordances and
all the affordances of this aspect of
the environment which is my hand and
that can also do many things just like
an iPhone can yeah yeah know I think I
think avoiding this dichotomy is really
really important right uh and so you
might think about the affordance of VR
or so right and that's like no that then
the whole environment becomes uh digital
in a sense and you you you you you you
duplicate the story but what we what we
encounter here is I think kind of
hybridity where at once I'm sitting
reading a book and next to me is a phone
which is a simple
object visually not much more
complicated than the book uh but that
allows me to to ENT completely uh
uh new
domain uh which at least intuitively
seems to be a completely new new domain
in the sense that one the layout of
action possibilities there is is
different uh to the kind of things that
I can do is so is so much more than than
uh I can do here and now uh in in in a
non digital environment
um so yeah avoiding that doomy is U
um is important and therefore it it all
needs to kind of be tied back to to
somehow like I think one field of
affordances that that
somehow in in whether you pick up your
phone or not kind of Mor so changes
changes changes shape and that that
that's a question about how to how to
how to think about
it
um and I guess this is this is probably
where where where where where
postphenomenology can offer some some
insights exactly
how um this field of affordances as a
kind of construct I think it's needed to
keep the kind of unity and to avoid the
kind of dualism that that you that you
were SK sketching but then still how do
the Technologies in the environment
which are not themselves the affordances
but but that that that that that allows
you to see through something into new
affordances how does that kind of
mediational process of intentionality
work and I think there are some Concepts
from from postphenomenology could could
help and I haven't in in in the kind of
more in either the inactive or the
eological psychology literature found
found any kind of good starting points
except for I think what what what is the
common ground for both an activism and
uh and postphenomenology namely the kind
of hopon kind of descriptions of of
hammers and Canes but that's that's
that's that's a two basic kind of
example to to to uh to pursue
further okay thanks for now to be
continued this
stop um okay so I'm I'm just keeping a
half eye on the the chat on YouTube and
but I do want to throw out a question of
my own which is going to be not terribly
well formed um but it's a question about
something that felt not terribly well
formed so I'm hoping that there some
kind of resonance there and that was the
concept of the agent that's in play here
because the you
essentially that to an extent was your
notion of these multiple anthropologies
as well what kind of agent are we
talking about and it feels to me that
the um there
are I guess it wasn't clear what make
what moves me from um one being one kind
of agent to another under different
circumstances because there are
certainly times when you know someone
might ask me what did you watch on the
television yesterday and I said well I
watched about 45 minutes of the Netflix
menu um and you know that was it and
then there are other dimes in which I
barely see the Netflix menu because I'm
flicking straight through to what it is
I'm going to and the the Netflix menu is
obviously designed to
encourage some sort you know some
aspects of that um and and less others
but um but my level of commitment
now obviously that you know just how
vast the Sea of potential options is you
know plays a role it makes it very
difficult to distinguish well what are
the difference between them what do I
care about um and and that is there's a
an important external not wanting to to
get into boundary questions but there's
there's an important environmental I
guess discussion about uh where my
desires are and how I recognize what I
want but I I guess I didn't even really
see much of a hint towards the well how
where do those desires come from or how
are they playing a role in in
structuring that field of
affordances yeah I'm just wondering what
what literature do you want to point to
and say well we'll use them for the
moment and then we'll figure out the
details as we
go yeah uh no great yeah
um so I think the two things here are uh
so if you read the more ecological
psychology literature on attention uh
there uh um
attention is always understood attention
and distraction are understood relative
to a
task and I mean in Psychology that that
that kind of makes sense right you give
people a task but in everyday life that
that that that's complicated and I guess
the task is already an advance over
having a goal right because a goal is
some something in your head and then how
does it shape your openness to
affordances not not not quite clear but
I think something like a behavior
setting also could be something in the
right direction where sometimes we have
the right kind of configuration of their
environment where it is
clear what the purpose of the situation
is I'm tired I deserve to uh to to to to
watch the new new new episode of the
crown I know this is the right kind of
series and then I've watched it before
so so uh this is what I'm going to do
and that that's a kind
of uh yeah engagement with technology
which which is then I think not
detrimental in in in any sense and and
just leads you to where you want to go
and and and and and that's fine
and so I
guess the kind of uh uh the kind of
really deep distraction kind of moments
are the facts the moments where there's
not really a task or where task shifting
is easier than engaging with the task so
sometimes I mean at least personally for
me it's like when when writing a paper
that's a bit
stuck every every progress should try to
make that paper uh uh one sentence later
the the task has somehow switched to to
to add it to social media to checking
your mail or whatever right so it's it's
it's it's very it's easier to switch
tasks than to uh make progress on on on
on one particular and of course yeah and
then the notion of task has its own
complexities and the notion of behavior
settings as well but I guess those would
be two kind of St stabilizers of
everyday actions that are that that that
could be made appropriate for for such a
kind of way of thinking I think without
bringing too much
trouble okay thanks yeah it I mean I
guess it gets at the how do affordances
compete um the the notion of the
affordance competition actually captures
um some some nice aspects of the
Dynamics I think but there's a it
becomes that as well well what is the
what are the mechanics I guess of that
competition how how are they actually
getting it you know yeah and and and
then uh uh I mean the wrong way to
pursue that would be like okay do do do
affords compete in the head in my nervos
system or do they compete in the world
right I mean no
that's got to be a more relational story
where there's only one competition
process that is that is surely uh aided
by by the kind of neurodynamics that's
going on competitive Dynamics but also
by the layout of the world and and and
and and and and the setting and and and
and the practice and part of somehow
combining those in in in uh without
completely losing the cognitive science
I think that that that would be a miss
and that's what you find in some of the
more post postphenomenology uh
literature and also not going completely
in Nur istic where in the end everything
happens in the brain I think that's
that's the from from from this
perspective the the
challenge um Fred is waving in his
camera here so I presume that's a it's
yeah it's it's it's
a um marrying ecological concepts and an
active Concepts is always something of a
challenge sens making is an interesting
term that sort of does service in both
worlds sometimes except that in the
ecological framework it's always a sense
making of an agent and in action
introduced the very interesting formal
device of participatory sens making
which destroys the notion of a rified
individualist experience so one could
expect two people sens making together
to have an entire if we're going to use
affordance language to have a different
typology of
affordances um which shifts from a
resolutely individualist and indeed
neurocentric view uh to to a much less
wellp specified place I think it's a
very interesting formal intervention
from sens making to participatory sens
making and I wonder if that has any Ram
if that side of the
formal thought figures of thought of an
action feature in your
analysis
um good no no so that they have not uh
uh yet and um
it's it's
it it's funny and interesting because I
think there there's a lot of
opportunities there to think about the
role of social media and the internet in
this in in this context right so there's
there's
uh um there's people working at at at
Google who do like qualitative studies
about about people's experience of of
social media and they write about the
kind of kind of continued sense of
social obligation because in my terms
the the affordance of replying to a
message is always there 24 hours a day
because this this this devic is there uh
and so it it it
gives that gives a kind of uh uh the
kind of messaging that that that's there
is there's two individuals that
reciprocally send messages to each other
so that that that kind of the the shape
of that kind of Technology seems to
reinforce a kind of
uh individualistic me against other
people me against the world uh kind of
kind of picture rather than I guess kind
of more participatory sense making where
that whole distinction kind of kind of
kind of kind of Falls away so I think
there that yeah I I haven't really gone
there and but I think there's great
great kind of both challenges and and
and opportunities there for such a kind
of framework yeah there's a really
interesting question about the temporal
Dynamics involved actually because I
know there's you know there be occasions
where you um you come across a
conversation on Twitter but it's a
conversation that's a day old or two
days old and it's like you don't want to
be the the you know someone raising the
the undead thread um but then on the
converse of that something vaguely
approaching participatory sense making
is involved in the pylon um where it's
like this is happening now go you know
everyone just yeah you either have the
the horrendous trolles pylon or you have
something that that sort of builds up to
you know where you have um a recent one
in Ireland was the there was a there's a
very um there's a television broadcast
that happens once a year called The Toy
Show which is a pre-Christmas commercial
thing that just this massive event the
entire country watches kids stay up late
um and they launched a a a funding
appeal and of course it became this
thing that everyone gets involved and
piles on the funding appeal so in the
course of about three and a half hours
they raiseed six million euro um but
because of precisely the the the kinds
of dynamics that that kind of um Twitter
and the internet allowed um and so that
there is a there's a Fascination uh some
really interesting questions about the
kinds of Dynamics I think particularly
the temporal dynamics that different
Technologies allow um that uh that there
is the possibility for particip sense
making through these these forms of
mediation as well and uh uh I think yeah
that's a great example I think another
one is also the fact that I mean on
Twitter you you interact by by text that
are written down right
so uh every statement there is by
definition the preposition uh and and so
in a conversation I can start with an
opposition and and and we find
convergence but the very fact that that
it's already written down right you you
cannot backtrack so easily on the things
that you said uh when when things are
written down than than when when things
are uh when you're in the conversation
where where indeed and kind of
participatory way you can you can find
common ground or something like this so
again I think one of the reasons why
discussions escalate so quickly is that
no this is you need to stand your ground
because you you you you you put down
your cards right and and Well normally
in the conversation we we we we don't do
that without shame you can you can you
can oh no yeah it's maybe yeah maybe I
phrase it in the wrong kind of way let
me rephrase it and that that kind of
turn taking participatory interactive
process is something that's just that's
just not not facilitated by that kind of
technological
structure natural language isn't literal
no no no no it's literal you know
written Languages by Def by definition
so it's a yeah it's a really good point
um so that is a we're sort of getting on
towards our our our finish time so I'll
um I I guess I'll give a warning for
anyone who wants to throw a a text up on
the the the YouTube chat just if you
want to jump in at a a last minute
intervention
um and Fred or Eric if either you'd like
to make a final comment but
um with with that I think we might um
bring the the session to a close so y
thank you very much for that
presentation and there's yeah lots of
nice food for thought that was a rich
ground for digging
[Music]
in well there's certainly plenty for a
three-year post talk that is for sure so
thank you thanks very much for giving
you time for the enel seminars and yeah
we look forward hopefully we can meet
again in person soon as well it be
fantastic
yeah great very
good okay thanks everyone and we will
see you next month for Manuel Aris esano
for who will kick off January 2021 if we
ever get there cool